Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection, Archives and Special Collections, Amherst College Library, Amherst College
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection, Archives and Special Collections, Amherst College Library, Amherst College
N/A
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
poetry manuscripts
Amherst College Amherst College Library Campus Box 2256 Amherst College P.O. Box 5000 Amherst, MA 01002-5000
This catalog aid was created from records created by Archives and Special Collections, Amherst College Library, and obtained by the Walt Whitman Archive. The original papers and catalogue records are held at Archives and Special Collections, Amherst College Library.
Restrictions on Original Materials:
Please consult with repository.
Scope and Content
Archives and Special Collections, Amherst College Library, holds manuscripts, galley proofs, correspondence, notes, and printed material by and about Walt Whitman. The papers are held mostly in "Miscellaneous Manuscripts," though a few items are scattered among other collections. The individual items described in this electronic finding aid are only those deemed poetry or prose manuscripts, and they are all held in "Miscellaneous Manuscripts."
Biographical Information
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Manuscripts; Poets, American--19th century
Item List
- Army Hospitals and Cases, 1888; amh.00010; xxx.00787; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  The first page of a fair copy draft of "Army Hospitals and Cases," an essay first published in the October 1888 issue of The Century magazine.
- [to enjoy the Panorama], about 1850; amh.00008; xxx.00787; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  The handwriting on this draft fragment indicates that it was written fairly early, probably before the the publication of Leaves of Grass in 1855. Most of the fragment describes a moving panorama, a popular form of entertainment during the antebellum period, and it is possible that this manuscript is part of a review that Whitman wrote while working as a newspaper editor. No published version of the manuscript has been located.
- Walt Whitman's Caution, about 1860; amh.00009; xxx.00035; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  This is a draft of Walt Whitman's Caution, a poem first appearing as one of the Messenger Leaves in Leaves of Grass ( 1860 ). The title of the poem was changed to To the States in the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves.
- 'Probably the largest Known animal', 1872–1892; amh.00005; xxx.01003; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  These notes by Whitman, beginning "Probably the largest Known animal," concern a "rorqual," a "razorback" or "finback" whale. The relationship of these notes to Whitman's published work is unknown.
- Thoughts, no. 4 ('Of ownership'), 1860; amh.00006; xxx.00148; xxx.00164; xxx.00167; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  This is a late draft of Thoughts, number 4 ("Of ownership"), which appeared first in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. The poem would later be split up into three separate poems.
- Fancies at Navesink, May 1885; amh.00003; xxx.00330; poetry 1 leaf handwritten printed
  This is a galley proof of four poems from Fancies of Navesink, a group of eight poems first published in The Nineteenth Century in August 1885: "The Pilot in the Mist," "Had I the Choice," "You Tides With Ceaseless Swell," and "Last of Ebb, and Daylight Waning." Signed, dated, and heavily annotated by Whitman.
- [In forming the book], undated; between 1873 and 1889; amh.00014; xxx.00410; xxx.00934; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  On one side of the leaf is a heavily revised prose fragment in which Whitman claims that his literary project has been to craft poetry which, rather than exemplifying conventional notions of poetic form, offers a faithful record of the writer's life and milieu. The relationship of this draft to any one of Whitman's published works is uncertain, though it resembles passages in several, including A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads (1888) and Note at End of Complete Poems and Prose" (1888). The other side of the leaf contains the last page of a letter to Whitman from James Matlack Scovel.
- National Literature, 1890 or 1891; amh.00017; xxx.00786; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  The first page of a draft essay that was published in the March 1891 issue of The North American Review under the title Have We a National Literature? Whitman's extensive revisions are done in ink and several different colors of pencil, and the two scraps of paper that constitute this manuscript leaf were pasted together by the author to create a single inscribed surface. The whole has been affixed, probably by Horace Traubel, one of Whitman's literary executors, to a backing sheet made of letterhead stationery from the office of "The Artsman." Traubel's note on the backing sheet's lower right corner is dated 1907 and indicates that he presented this item to William Gable.
- [It is in itself], about 1873; amh.00002; xxx.00263; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  This is an early draft, with revisions, of the paragraph that introduced Prayer of Columbus when it was first published in the March 1874 issue of Harper's Monthly Magazine and then in Two Rivulets (1876). Later printings of the poem deleted the introduction.
- [Drum-Taps], between 1865-1892; amh.00004; xxx.00172; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  This note indicates the proper location for the Drum-Taps poems in the page sequence of what was apparently a manuscript or some other pre-publication form of Whitman's poems. Whitman first used the title Drum-Taps for a volume of poems published in 1865. The title was also applied to a cluster of poems within later editions of Leaves of Grass.